And then, the day came.
It had been a bright, sunny day. The sun was setting, huge against the orange sky. The forest sounds were getting quieter, ready for the night.
I looked around me: I tried to memorise the colours, the smells of my homeland, I packed them all in my brain, I stored them safely to keep myself warm during my journey.
I looked at my mother’s eyes. She was proud. She was terrified.
She had done the journey herself, though she had always refused to talk about it.
“I’ll be fine, Ma. Don’t worry.”
“Of course you’ll be fine”, she said, then she looked away. She didn’t want me to see her doubt.
I flew to the top of our tree to warm up.
I looked at the open sky. It was so huge, you couldn’t see the end of it. I felt dizzy.
Despite the heat, I started to shiver, my heart pounding in my chest. How could I possibly do this?
Maybe it was a big mistake. Maybe I wasn’t ready. Maybe I could wait, just a little longer.
I heard a bird laugh behind me. It was a fat bird of paradise, munching on berries.
“What’s up with you willow warbler? Having second thoughts?”
“I’m just stretching my wings, getting ready for the flight, that’s all.”
“No kidding. A tiny bird like you, making it to Europe? How much do you weigh? 10g?”
“8. Still, it’s not the weight that counts, it’s the spirit.
But how could you understand? Birds of paradise have it easy. Big guns like you take all the food. Come summer, there will be nothing left for us.
And predators are getting stronger too, they are just waiting for an opportunity to munch on the little ones too weak to escape.
So don’t talk to me like I have a choice. Live or die, that’s the only choice we have. And I choose to live.“
And then, without another thought, I opened my little green wings and took off.